we move now to the part of the kernel
that it's the I/O subsystem we are going
to look at some specific aspects and things
that are done at this level in the kernel
so the services we are going to look or the
things we're going to discuss here it's the
scheduling of input and output we will
see buffering caching and spooling mechanisms
we will discuss also a bit of types
of errors we can handle and different ways
to handle them and also we will discuss
rapidly why there are also needs for protecting
specific parts of the memory and that is also
part of what the I/O subsystem does
so scheduling we discussed many times I made
many examples of processes that need to write
something on disk and then they go into
the waiting state and so on so it turns out
that the requests that are made by many processes
are not necessarily executed in the same order
they are made
the operating system the I/O part
of the kernel subsystem can
optimize and change the order in which it
serves the different requests depending on
the hardware is interacting with the example
here would be for a rotating disk
so if let's say you have three applications
one two and three one wants to read or write
something at the end of the disk the second
one wants something at the beginning of the
disk and the third one needs a block
near the middle of the disk then you
see that if you're just going in this order then
you have to go to the end of the disk then
back to the beginning of the disk and then
go to the middle of the disk
if you have the ability of shuffle
the order and go in a different order it might
be that it's actually better to execute this
requests in the order two three and one you
can start from the beginning of the disk especially
if you are already there
read what you need to read then go to the
middle go and then go to the end of course
it is specific to the hardware this is a rotating
disk an SSD disk doesn't really
incur different times depending on how far you
need to go in the disk
so this kind of optimization wouldn't really
make sense now as always tradeoffs this is
an optimization that can increase performance
so the scheduling requests in specific orders
depending on the hardware but then you will
need to keep extra information
so basically it is no longer true that as
soon as you get something from the disk that
is information that is for the first process
or for the process control block that is
first in the queue of processes waiting for
the disk because you are no longer serving
requests in order somehow you need to add
extra information
in each process control block to keep track
of what it is that they are waiting for and
when you get something from the disk then
you can find out which one is the process
control block that you can move back to the
writing queue the operating system the kernel
will also use buffers
so when you are accumulating data that will
later be sent to the disk or to the network
you actually keep it that the memory you keep
accumulating that in memory that's a buffer
and once the buffer is full then you transfer
the data to the device
now you actually need two buffers is the double
buffer mechanism because once one buffer is
full and you start transferring the content
of the buffer to disk for example that will
take a certain amount of time and you cannot
keep adding stuff to the buffer in that amount
of time
so what you do is that you write that buffer
and you start using a second buffer to feed stuff
and then you keep switching between the two
every time one is full you stop using the other
and you write the first to disk or to whatever
device you're interacting with
this is also done because of the different
speeds with which the devices can read
and write data here you have just some example
number this is the old slide but it still shows
what I'm trying to say here and there
is a second mechanism that is used by the
kernel which is caching and that
is similar to what we discussed already when
we were discussing caches at the hardware level
for the memories so there are copies that
are kept at the operating system in memory
at the memory by the operating system
so that if you try to access that thing again in
the immediate future you already have that
in memory you don't need to interact again with
the device and also the kernel will take
care of creating a queue and keep and holding up
the output for specific devices if these devices
can only serve one request at the time
so this is handled automatically by the operating
system and this is the spooling mechanism when
it comes to errors as you can imagine the
kernel will have several routines several
parts that are dedicated to handle errors
and here you can distinguish between permanent
and transient errors
maybe you have experienced this yourself if you use
a rotating disk (but also
SSD disks) rotating disks they tend to
fail after a while and some sectors some parts
of it they stop working
so you can still use the disk but some portions
of it will become unusable so when that starts
happening in your machine eventually that
hard disk will just be corrupted so it's a
sign that it's time to change
the disk still the operating system has a
routine to find out that some sectors might
be damaged and it will still try to operate
with the remaining ones so all these things
are part of the handling off or they are supported
by the fact that there are components in the
kernel that are about handling errors for
input or output operations and then of
course that is the part about protection this
we discussed basically since the beginning
of the course I think I'm not saying anything
new at this point the very first thing we
discussed was system calls
and now at this point you can probably understand
how a system call is a complicated thing that
requires interaction with many parts of the
operating system and everything is done in
the spirit of protection so that you basically
protect the users from the hardware but most likely the hardware
from the user and from the different processes
here you have some example of protection mechanisms